Guide to the Cynthia Brown papers, 1975-1986 MS2312
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Cynthia Brown Office for Civil Rights collection
1975-1986
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Brown, Cynthia G.
MS2312
3.5 Linear Feet 7 document boxes
This collection contains correspondence, reports, legal documents, clippings, and briefing books produced and collected by Cynthia Brown during the course of her work between 1975 and 1982, first as the principal deputy of the Department of Health, Education and Welfare's Office for Civil Rights, and subsequently as the Assistant Secretary for Civil Rights in the U.S. Department of Education. It also includes a draft of her memoir, "Twenty Years On: Equity in Education and Civil Rights Enforcement," written in 1986.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, reports, legal documents, clippings, and briefing books produced and collected by Cynthia Brown during the course of her work between 1975 and 1982, first as the principal deputy of the Department of Health, Education and Welfare's Office for Civil Rights, and subsequently as the Assistant Secretary for Civil Rights in the U.S. Department of Education. It also includes a draft of her memoir, "Twenty Years On: Equity in Education and Civil Rights Enforcement," written in 1986.
Major topics covered in this collection include bilingual education -- particularly the Lau v. Nichols Supreme Court case and its policy implications -- as well as enforcement of laws against discrimination in education by race and gender.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cynthia Brown, 2012 (2012.083)
Biographical / Historical
Cynthia G. Brown was the first Assistant Secretary for Civil Rights in the U.S. Department of Education, appointed in 1980 by President Carter. Prior to that position, she served as principal deputy of the Department of Health, Education and Welfare's Office for Civil Rights in the 1970s.
After leaving government service, Brown was a co-director of the nonprofit Equality Center, and a director of the Resource Center on Educational Equity of the Council of Chief State School Officers. Brown is currently Vice President for Education Policy at the Center for American Progress, a think tank in Washington, D.C.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: Bilingual education; Office for Civil Rights, Department of Education; and Memoir.
Other Finding Aids
For related materials, please see also:
Phyllis McClure Civil Rights in Education collection
William L. Taylor papers
Educational change; Education, Bilingual -- United States; Brown, Cynthia G.
- Bilingual education, 1975-1982; Series 1; 2 Linear Feet 4 document boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains correspondence, briefing books, regulations, clippings, and laws regarding bilingual education, with a particular focus on the Lau v. Nichols Supreme Court case and its policy implications. The material dates from 1975 to 1982.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Bilingual education -- Briefing Book draft [1 of 2], 1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bilingual education -- Briefing Book draft [2 of 2], 1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bilingual education -- Lau [1 of 3], undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bilingual education -- Lau [2 of 3], undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bilingual education -- Lau [3 of 3], undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bilingual education -- Lau evaluation, 1979; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bilingual education -- Lau policy, 1979; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bilingual education -- Lau regulations [1 of 2], 1980; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bilingual education -- Lau regulations [2 of 2], 1980; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bilingual education -- laws, 1979; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bilingual education papers [1 of 3], 1982; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bilingual education papers [2 of 3], 1982; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bilingual education papers [3 of 3], 1982; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Bilingual education -- NPRM [1 of 4], 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bilingual education -- NPRM [2 of 4], 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bilingual education -- NPRM [3 of 4], 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Bilingual education -- NPRM [4 of 4], 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Bilingual education -- state laws, 1980; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Bilingual education -- testimony, 1975-1978; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Bilingual education -- Title VII clipping, 1982; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Bilingual education -- U.S. v. Texas, 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Briefing Book on Civil Rights Language Minority Notice of Proposed Rulemaking [1 of 2], 1981; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Briefing Book on Civil Rights Language Minority Notice of Proposed Rulemaking [2 of 2], 1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Lau Briefing Book [1 of 2], undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lau Briefing Book [2 of 2], undated; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Lau coalition, 1976-1981; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Lau guidelines, 1980; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Lau regulation background book, 1980; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Office for Civil Rights, Department of Education, 1977-1982; Series 2; 1.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes
  This series contains correspondence, reports, manuals, legal documents, and legislative materials documenting Brown's work in the Office for Civil Rights at the Department of Education. The material dates from 1977 to 1982. Some material also comes from Brown's tenure at the Office for Civil Rights at the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. This can be confusing because the offices in both departments were called Office for Civil Rights.
  - Bureau of Hearings and Appeals, 1977; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Civil Rights Task Force workplan, Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Office for Civil Rights briefing for confirmation hearing of Judge Hufstedler, 1979; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Office for Civil Rights, Department of Education Transition, 1980; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Office for Civil Rights issues, 1979; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Office for Civil Rights legislative history, 1980; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Office for Civil Rights Manual Reporting System, 1978-1979; Series 2 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Office for Civil Rights manuals [1 of 2], undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Office for Civil Rights manuals [2 of 2], undated; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Office for Civil Rights/Office of General Counsel relationship, 1980; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Office for Civil Rights -- Office of Management and Budget decision, 1979; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Office for Civil Rights organization, 1980; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Office for Civil Rights organizational proposal, 1981; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Office for Civil Rights -- private schools, 1977; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Office for Civil Rights Quality Assurance Handbook, 1982; Series 2 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Memoir, 1986; Series 3; 3 folder(s)
  This series contains a draft of Brown's 1986 memoir Twenty Years On: Equity in Education and Civil Rights Enforcement. It was published in 1987 by the National Center for Policy Alternatives as Twenty Years On: New Federal and State Roles to Achieve Equity in Education, and is out of print.
  - Twenty Years On: Equity in Education and Civil Rights Enforcement [1 of 3], 1986; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Twenty Years On: Equity in Education and Civil Rights Enforcement [2 of 3], 1986; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Twenty Years On: Equity in Education and Civil Rights Enforcement [3 of 3], 1986; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)